Alexey **Bochkarev**

Researcher in Mathematical Optimization / Operations Research PhD candidate, Clemson University

✓ abochka@g.clemson.edu www.bochkarev.io • alex-bochkarev ¥ @a_bochka **a** @abochka

Research interests

Mathematical optimization, theory and applications, especially:

- Combinatorial optimization,
- Network optimization and interdiction,
- Decision diagrams and dynamic programming,
- Applications of reinforcement learning techniques.

Applications: So far my research has been driven more by methodological questions, but I do have some experience of implementing applied models in industry. Also, due to my background I have a special interest in optimization related to electricity markets: pricing / OPF / economic dispatch / infrastructure planning, etc.

Research experience / current projects

 $(more \ \square)$

- Align-BDD: seeking to obtain computational benefits and sensitivity information by representing a combinatorial problem as a collection of Binary Decision Diagrams (BDDs). The project involves creating a heuristic to enforce a certain structural property for a pair of BDDs and building a related "computational pipeline" for a specific, hard optimization problem: a variant of the facility location.
- **DSPI:** applying game-playing and reinforcement learning techniques to the Dynamic Shortest-path Interdiction problem, in a framework of a Monte-Carlo Search Tree based algorithm.

Both projects involve design and implementation of an algorithm and the related computational experiments.

Research supervisor: Dr. J. Cole Smith.

Working papers and conference presentations

- Working paper: A. A. Bochkarev, J.C. Smith, On Aligning Non-Order-Associated Binary Decision Diagrams, revision submitted to INFORMS Journal on Computing. (First submission: 2020/08/22)
- Presentation: INFORMS Annual Meeting, 2020 (virtual), BDD section.

Grants and awards

- Clemson University Doctoral Dissertaion Completion Grant (support for Fall 2021)
- Graduate Travel Grant (to participate in INFORMS Annual Meeting 2021)
- International Teaching Fellowship from Clemson University (partial support in 2020, training in teaching)

Education

PhD Industrial Engineering (2018-2021 exp)

Clemson University, US Operations Research track

MSc/BSc Appl. Math and Physics (2004–2010)

Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Russia

M.A. Economics (2008-2010)

New Economic School, Russia

(Human) Languages

English (fluent), Russian (native), German (A1).

Technical skills

 $(more \ \square)$

Main programming stack:

- Python (gurobi, CBC, numpy/pandas, etc.)
- R (ggplot, dplyr, tidyverse),
- Julia (JuMP/gurobi, LightGraphs),
- C++ (gurobi, armadillo/BLAS, boost).

Basic knowledge: PyTorch, Java, Matlab/Octave.

Other technical skills: PBS (comp cluster), GNU/Linux, bash; make, git, LATEX, Emacs, basic GIS (QGIS), Inkscape, beamer / PPT / reveal.js, Jupyter.

Teaching experience



- Designed and delivered two 4-days mini-courses aimed at gifted high-school students and early undergrads for School for Molecular and Theoretical Biology (SMTB) and Puschino Winter School (ZPSh), both Russian and English versions:
 - "Practical Introduction to Probability Theory", ZPSh-2021, SMTB-2021
 - "A Glimpse into Algorithms", SMTB-2020 (workshop), SMTB-2021 (course)
- TA in "Intro probability" undergrad course at Clemson University (IE3600), Summer 2021

Service and volunteering / Community

Besides teaching at summer and winter schools (above), I have been doing some work under the umbrella of Clemson University INFORMS Student Chapter:

- serving on the Executive Board: as a Secretary (2020) and President (2021),
- organized a "Journal club on Network optimization and interdiction" (2021),
- designed and delivered "OR Tech Seminar" a series of four workshops on "research toolbox".

Industry experience

The Federal Grid (FGC UES)

(2013-2017)

Electricity transmission, Moscow, Russia

Role: Team head, modeling and analytics

Focus: Performance benchmarking (branches), operational efficiency improvement. Internal regulations/KPI, strategy, analytics / modeling, and presentations.

Ministry of Energy of Russia

(2013)

Public service: energy (electricity), Moscow, Russia

Role: Deputy team head

Focus: Electricity transmission and distribution grids, benchmarking, economic efficiency. Analytics, presentations.

Roland Berger Strategy Consultants GmbH

(2010-2013)

Strategic consulting, Moscow, Russia

Role: Intern \rightarrow Junior Consultant \rightarrow Consultant

Focus: Infrastructure and construction. Strategy and performance: market entry, supply/demand modeling, growth strategy, efficiency improvement. Internal knowledge sharing, modeling, presentations.